<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>

	<string name="startpage_route1">Green route\n\n</string>
	<string name="startpage_route1_subtitle">Narrow Alleys</string>
	<string name="startpage_route2">Purple route\n\n</string>
	<string name="startpage_route2_subtitle">Churches of Gouda</string>
	<string name="startpage_distance">Distance: </string>
	
	<string name ="startpage_infotext"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = \'aqua\' ; >Gouda</font></h2><p>This app offers you walkabouts in Gouda\'s historical center. Watch the video for how to use this app.</p><p>In Hollands \"Randstad\" area the city of Gouda has 70,939 inhabitants on a surface of 19,92 km². It is a regional center within the \"Green Heart\", the part of the Randstad where we find more nature and agriculture. Gouda lies where the rivers \"Gouwe\" and \"Hollandse Ijssel\" merge. Thanks to inland shipping across these rivers Gouda grew to an important Dutch city during the middle-ages. The city acquired city-rights in 1272 and became Hollands 5th largest city. In the center we can still find a great number of historical and monumental buildings, of which the City Hall and the St John are probably the most famous. Besides that Gouda is renowned for its chees which is traded on thursdays touristic cheesemarket. Also the city is known for the manufacture of candles, pipes, syrup wafers and the yearly Candle-night. The green route offers you a short walk in the center and shows you a lot of small alleys and hidden places. The purple route guides you along Gouda\'s churches and places of worship.</p>]]></string>
    
    <string name="app_name">Gouda City Walks</string>
    <string name="action_settings">Settings</string>
    <string name="placeholderstring">Dit is het stadhuis van Gouda. Op de voorgevel zie je beelden van de graven van Holland, zij hebben destijds dit grote gebouw betaald en daar wilden ze wel een beeld voor terug #8230</string>
    
    
    
    
    <string name="infotext_template"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = \'aqua\' ; >Title here </font></h2><p>headingtext</p><p>Further Text</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext1"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #00FFFF ; >City Hall</font></h2><p>At first the City Hall had a administrative function. Through the years the building has been used in many different ways. For instance, it has been a law court but also a market hall for meat. Until 2012 the City Council met here and used the building for official receptions.  At the moment hundreds of marriages are affirmed here. At the yearly Candle Night the City Hall is a fairy tale like decor.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext2"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #00FF00 ; >Korte Groenendaal</font></h2><p>Gouda is a city of crafts. Traditionally the farmers cheese that was being made in the region was traded on the thursday cheese market. The cheese was being weighed and traded on the market square. After the emergence of factory cheese the cheese market lost her significance. The thursday market is only a remnant of an old tradition being kept alive for our visitors. At the beginning of the 19th century the first syrup wafers were being baked in Gouda. More then 100 bakers lived in the city in that century. Nowadays, only 4 of the are left, one of which is at the corner Naaiersstraat - Lange Groenendaal. Each of these bakers makes the wafers according a secret recipe,  which is carefully guarded. As an export article and as a touristic attraction the syrup wafer is an important product. </p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext3"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #FFFF00 ; >Naaiersstraat The four crowned ones.</font></h2><p>Probably the image on the ornamental border existed before 1532. It is likely that one of the former owners, the mason Cornelisz Jacobsz, made or let made the image. Also John the Stonecutter is mentioned as the possible artist of the ornament. The image does not only depict the work of masons and stonecutters, but is also a homage to the four crowned ones, 4 martyrs from the 4th century who refused to make a tin god idol statue for the Roman emperor Diocletan in the year 306. They paid with their lives for this refusal. In chests of lead they were dumped into a river. However, the story remained and the martyrs became patron saints of all construction workers. On the empty spot in the middle there was probably an image of St Mary.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext4"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #f0f8aa ; >Museum of Resistance </font></h2><p>The museum is housed in a former bank building, the bank of the widows Knox and Dortland. Theme of the museum is the resistance against the occupation during the second world war. In the tea garden you will found several replica\'s of Dutch resistance monuments. </p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext5"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #7FFFD4 ; >Lady\'s Tower</font></h2><p>The chapel and tower, dedicated to st Mary, were built in the period 1489 to 1494 as a commission of the Rosicrucian fraternity. The chapel was used as a school for deprived girls, they got free education in reading and worship. After the reformation the chapel was used for protestant worshipping services, although later on they used the Saint John  for this purpose. All the churchbenches were moved to the Saint John in 1574 and the chapel was demolished shortly afterwards. However, the tower was allowed to remain. The tower bell dates from 1590. The Latin text on the bell translates : \"If God favours us who will be against us. Thomas Both made me in 1590\"</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext6"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #8FBC8F ; >Jansenius Courtyard</font></h2><p>Dutch courtyard houses were built from the 13th to the beginning of the 20th century. A courtyard was a patio where public facilities like a washing area and a toilet were present. These courtyards were usually surrounded by houses .In many cases they had a wall around them, with two entrances that were locked during the nights. These \"Hofjes\" were being managed by foundations. Gouda knows quite a lot of these courtyards but many of them have disappeared due to sloppy management. Therefore Jansenius Courtyard is only hardly recognisable as a \"Hofje\".</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext7"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #FF8C00 ; >Stairsbridge</font></h2><p>The Stairsbridge(Trappenbrug) is the last one of her sort, although many have existed in Gouda. Because of the high water level a stairs like constructions were built over the water, to let the ships loaded with peat through. Already in 1507 there was a stone bridge here. It was also mentioned \"Dirt alley bridge\". Where you just came from was called the Dirt Alley, leading to the dump at what is now Regentesseplantsoen. For obvious reasons the Dirt Alley was renamed to the nondescriptive \"Long Sidestreet\".</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext8"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #6495ED ; >Looierspoort(Tanners Gate) Lange Groenendaal</font></h2><p>The Tanners gate is named after the many tanners who had their occupation here. Until the 19th century there were gardens from big houses at the Turfmarkt. In 1879 several gardens were sold and used to build 12 small houses. These houses consist of one room on the ground and one room in the attic. In 1996 these houses were saved from demolition and subsequently renovated. One of the cutest shopping areas of Gouda is the Lange Groenendaal. In this street you will find special shops and boutiques like a wine store, a deli,  a coffee and tea shop, and gift shops.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext9"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #C0C0C0 ; >Fishing grounds (Visbanken)</font></h2><p>The fishing ground on the side of the Hoge Gouwe is also called Corn Exchange, although it has always been a fish market for the fishermen from outside Gouda. The fishing ground  on the side were you are standing was a fish market for the Gouda fishermen. For tourists it would be interesting when fish would be sold again here. Unfortunately the demands of the law are so stern that it would be impossible for traders to take this up. However, there is a parallel with the past : Whoever sold stinking fish, could account for a vast penalty fee, and his fish was subsequently dumped into the Gouwe.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext10"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #FFFF00 ; >Dark Sluice(Donkere sluis) / Wijdstraat</font></h2><p>The Dark Sluice is in origin one of the oldest Dutch sluices. From the Hollande Ijssel river one could reach the Oude Rijn river and eventually the Ij in Amsterdam via this sluice. This route was internationally heavily used. Since 1954 the sluice is being put out of use and renovated as a monument of water management. The Wijdstraat is a street in the center of Gouda, adjacent to the market. You will find nice shops and restaurants here. The street is renowned for its \"Gouda Gallery of crafts\". Watch the stones of the pavement carefully, you will find the names of all the crafts that once were practised in Gouda, like goldsmith, candlemaker or pipesmaker.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext11"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #F5F5F5 ; >Synagogue</font></h2><p>This was the religious center of the Gouda Jewish community. In 1798 they bought an empty Baptist shelter church. That is, a church that is not recognisable from the outside as a church. It was transformed into a synagogue  in 1823. In the 20th century the amount of Jews in Gouda dramatically dropped : only a few of the 500 deportated Jews returned from the concentration camps. In 1950 the synagogue was sold. The stone above the door says \"Free evangelical community\" but also the Jewish foundation Tsedaca will commune here.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext12"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #40E0D0 ; >Dawn church(De Morgenstond)</font></h2><p>At the Lage Gouwe you will find the Dawn Church (De Morgenstond), the building of the Gouda Pentecostal Community.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext13"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #D8BFD8 ; >Christian reformed church</font></h2><p>The church building of the Christian Reformed Church can be found in Gouda\'s historical center at the Hoge Gouwe 141.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext14"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #B0E0E6 ; >Old Catholic church</font></h2><p>Vicar Petrus Purmerent bought a house at the Hoge Gouwe 113 in 1630 and furnished it for prayer ceremonies. This shelter church, dedicated to John the Baptist grew during the time to what is now the Old-Catholic church. As long as the complex served as a shelter church it was necessarily hidden behind a row of living houses. In the roof of the current presbytery we can still see traces of the first church hall that was made in that day. In the ages afterwards adjacent houses were bought and in their gardens a second church hall was built.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext15"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #87CEEB ; >Sint Joostkapel</font></h2><p>The Saint Joost chapel dates from the 15th century. It was dedicated to Saint Joost, the patron saint of turf- and bagcarriers in Gouda. He was also called by women to help with a childbirth. After the reformation the chapel was used as a turf-shed. Later on the fire brigade used it to stall ladders and buckets. In 1680 the city council sold the building to the Lutheran Community, who renovated the building en officially took it in use in 1682. Take a closer look at the pavement on the side of the church, you will see   many letters. They sum up to 95, all beginning letters of the 95 theses Luther nailed on the door of the Wittenberg church in 1517. Besides the Lutheran community, also the Federation Gouda uses this chapel. This federation is a union of Baptists, Remonstrants, and Liberal Protestants.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext16"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #FFC0CB ; >Nour Mosque</font></h2><p>In the sixties of the last century there is a big labour shortage in the Netherlands. As a response to this large demand many people from the South come to the Netherlands. Countries of origin are, Spain, Italy, Turkey and Morocco. In Gouda especially a lot of people from the North-West of Morocco come. Although it might have not been their initial intention to stay permanently here, many decide to let their families come over to make the permanent migration a fact. Like Christians have a need for their own buildings of worship, the first generation of Muslims also liked to have their own spaces for gathering and prayer. This first Mosque is called \"The Light\" (Nour). Later on two other mosques were built, \"El Fath\" in the Spieringstraat and \"As-Salaam\" in the Oosterwei quarter.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext17"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #00FFFF ; >Barbaratower</font></h2><p>The Barbaratower is the remaining of the chapel of the Saint Barbara hospital which stood at the corner Kuipersstraat and Keizerstraat. The hospital was built in 1468 by the guild of Saint Barbara. A chapel besides the hospital was built in 1505. Saint Barbara was one of the so called \"Helpers in distress\". She was paricularly called for protection against the black death, the plague. Later on hospital and chapel also got a function as a school for the poor. When you look up at the tower clock you will notice that the clock has only one pointer. Because of this the tower got the nickname \"Silly tower\". However, others believe that the tower got its nickname because the clockwork broke down regularly.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext18"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #f0f8aa ; >Remonstrant church</font></h2><p>What you see here is the portal building of the Remonstrant church. Gouda used to be  a center for this protestant branch, that held more liberal opinions towards for example the doctrine of predestination. It was forbidden to hold ceremonies for the Remonstrants but nevertheless they communed : in private houses, outside the city walls, and even on ice. In 1629 the remonstrants bought a house in the Keizerstraat. The back part was furnished as a preaching place, while the front part served as a presbytery. The church was torn down in 1870 after wich a new little church arose with the portal building as the entrance. The church in the back was demolished in 1988.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext19"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #7FFFD4 ; >Gouwekerk </font></h2><p>Franciscan Vicar Gregorius Simpernel founded a Roman Catholic shelter church here in the first half of the 17th century. Initially the services took place in a normal house, \"Het Cromhout\", which was replaced with a newly built church in 1732. After this church burned down in 1767, another church was made according to the the design you see now. In 1853 the church was officially recognised by the Dutch Bishops. It got the name Saint Joseph Church. The order of the Franciscans left the church halfway the 20th century and the order of \"Our Sweet Lady Ascension\" took over. In 1979 the missionay foundation \"Johan Maasbach\" took over. It was local law that if catholics lived in the public orphanage they could not be buried on a catholic burial site. Therefore the catholic community bought a house besides the church and built their own orphanage which was managed by German nuns. This building can be recognized by a rich Renaissance style, which you can see for example in the iron fence, the doors and the bows. </p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext20"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #8FBC8F ; >Guesthousechapel (Gasthuiskapel)</font></h2><p>This chapel is not in use as a place of worship but is part of the Gouda museum.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext21"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #FF8C00 ; >Saint Johns Church (St Janskerk)</font></h2><p>With its lenght of 123 meters the St Johnschurch is Netherlands longest church building. The church is built in Gothic style and is renowned for its stained glass windows. The church services are held by the Gouda Reformed Church, but many other activities also find place in this church. The church is dedicated to Saint John, the Baptist.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext22"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #6495ED ; >Jerusalemchapel</font></h2><p>At the end of the 15th century priest and vicar of the Saint John, Gijsbert Raet had made a pilgrimage to Jerusalem. Back in Gouda he ordered to make a chapel according to the model of the Holy Grave Church in Jerusalem. This chapel is the best preserved of this type in the Netherlands. It is 12-sided and used to have an altar with a painted triptych above it. Besides that there was a golden ceremonial robe and a monument in memory of the Holy Grave. The chapel is no more in use as a place of worship but is used for arts and culture.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext23"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #FF44AA ; >Mosque El-Fath (\"Victory\")</font></h2><p></p>]]></string>
	<string name="infotext235"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = \'aqua\' ; >Council of believers</font></h2><p>This building at Peperstraat 20 was made by Gouda manufacturer Pieter de Raadt in 1897. This council has as peculiarity that each male member can speak during a worship session. The building is known for its rich variety of architectural styles.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext24"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #FFFF00 ; >Poor mans church (Armenkerk)</font></h2><p>The start of the 19th century was not a prosperous time for Gouda, it was the poorest city of the country. Many impoverished people didn\'t want to show up any more in the imposing Saint Johns Church. In their miserable condition they didn\'t feel at home there any more. For this group a low threshold church was built here. Soon it got the nick-name \"Poor mans church\". It was beneficial to go to this church. From  the diaconate they got a higher welfare payment. There is a typical Dutch expression for this situation: \"Whose word you hear, whose bread you eat.\"</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext25"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #98FB98 ; >The Tollhouse</font></h2><p>Gouda\'s tollhouse lies on the strategic spot where the rivers \"Hollandse Ijssel\" and \"Gouwe\" came together. Because Gouda was the only connection between the Southern and the Northern parts of Holland, collection of toll was a lucrative business.  The city of Gouda therefore resisted heavily against better or new connections between the North and the South, because an important income source would be stopped. Not only the toll money was of importance here, but also the spendings of the sailors who were deliberately forced to wait for several days before they could move on. After the French came in 1795 the tolls were discarded.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext26"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #FF4500 ; >Carding mill (De Volmolen)</font></h2><p>The grand carding mill is from 1632 and was driven by the tides. Very early on people made use of the tides. That is because the Hollandse Ijssel river stands in open connection with the sea. With ebb the water is 60 cm below sea level, but with flood the level is about 120 cm above sea level. The water levels in the city lie at 70 cm below so that at any time water could flow into the city. The carding mill made use of this principle, in fact it is a water mill where the water flows below the building and where a waterwheel propulses the machinery on ground level. The carding mill processed wool to make linnen.  In the early days the process consisted of stamping with feet on the wool which was in bathtubs with water, urine and other additions. The mill replaced this tedious labour and became an early example of industrial mechanisation. Around 1900 the mill was drastically renovated and became a  warehouse for cheese, so that few things remind us of that this was once a mill.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext27"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #FFDAB9 ; >The castle and the mill</font></h2><p>Here, besides the mouth of the harbour, was a castle, built by Jan van Blois in 1361. From here he could control the harbour entrance and ask toll money. The city council demolished the castle in 1577 to be released from this feodal source of power, in order to take the taxes into their own hands. Below in the park you can find the tower foundations that were dug up in 1938. But few things remind us of ever being a castle here. You will also find a windmill here \"Het Slot\" , which is a reference to the castle. It is a cornmill and originally built on the remainders of the castle in 1582. The mill burned down in 1831, after which a stone windmill was made which you can still see here in a working state.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext28"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #FFDAB9 ; >Houtmansplantsoen</font></h2><p>The park was made after 1830 when space along the canals (Singels) was created by the demolition of the city walls. Initially the park was a narrow green corridor along the canals. The park is named after the brothers Cornelis and Frederik de Houtman, who sailed to the East Indies with the first Dutch colonial expedition. Since 1880 there is a monument for the two brothers. On sunday afternoons you can go to the square here to enjoy free music events.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext29"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #87CEEB ; >Swanenburg courtyard (Swanenburgs hofje)</font></h2><p>This \"Hofje\" was built by the reformed diacony in 1692 on the \"burnt yard\". Until 1572 here stood the Saint Margareth monastery, probably the oldest womens monastery of Gouda. A commemorative stone of this place can be found in the outside wall of the Gouda museum.</p>]]></string>
    <string name="infotext30"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = #FFDAB9 ; >Huize Groeneweg</font></h2><p>Huize Groeneweg was originally a monastery. After the reformation it was being used as a school. Halfway the 19th century it was a place where beggars were being put to work. In the 20th century the house became living space for elder people. This is one of Gouda\'s eldest buildings.</p>]]></string>
   
    <string name="infotext85"><![CDATA[<h2><font color = \'aqua\' ; >Attention! </font></h2><p>Don\'t miss the entry of the small alley and watch the photo!</p>]]></string>

</resources>